<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Discourse about conscience, relating to the present differences among us in opposition to both extreams of popery and fanaticism.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36078</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1568</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8393</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12381402</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12381402</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60769</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36078)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60769)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 937:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Discourse about conscience, relating to the present differences among us in opposition to both extreams of popery and fanaticism.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>43 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Crooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conscience --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Religion --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60769:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE ABOUT CONSCIENCE, Relating to the <hi>Preſent Differences</hi> AMONG US.</p>
            <p>In Oppoſition to both <hi>Extreams</hi> OF <hi>POPERY</hi> and <hi>FANATICISM.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Crooke,</hi> at the <hi>Green Dragon</hi> without <hi>Temple Bar,</hi> next <hi>Devereux Court.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:60769:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:60769:2"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE ABOUT CONSCIENCE, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THE Deſign of this ſhort Diſcourſe, is to treat about the Nature and Office of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> how, or in what reſpect it doth oblige; which, as it appears by the Practice of ſome Men, laying Claim thereunto, ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h been either groſly miſtaken, or wilfully abuſed: But be it either one way, or other, I am ſure it has been made the common Cloak and Excuſe for ſome of the greateſt Diſorders, and unwarrantable Proceedings, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt the peaceable Communion of our Church, but the legal, and well-eſtabliſhed Government of the State. Now if theſe few Lines, charitably of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, may conduce any thing toward the rectifying of ſuch Miſtakes, and conſequently the preventing the like Abuſes in any that are willing to be undecei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, I have all the End I aim at; if not, I ſhall have however this Satisfaction, that what I have here of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered towards it, is done with all the Kindneſs and Charity that poſſibly I could, without betraying the Cauſe I have undertaken, or doing Injury to that Church, whoſe Communion I have here took Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to recommend, and plead for: And therefore
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60769:3"/>without any tedious Preface, or fruitleſs Apology, I ſhall addreſs my ſelf to the Subject in hand, and that in a very plain and impartial manner.</p>
            <p>Now in my Diſcourſe hereupon, I ſhall ſhew you,</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> What <hi>Conſcience</hi> is, or what is included in the Notion of it.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> What it is to live up to <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That notwithſtanding <hi>Conſcience,</hi> by many perſons pretending to it, hath been, and is ſtill abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, yet ought not to be neglected, or laid aſide.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> What things <hi>Conſcience</hi> ought chiefly to be concerned for, or exerciſed about.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> To offer a few things by way of Advice, concerning the governing of our ſelves, with relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to our <hi>Conſciences.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>From whence you may perceive, that I intend to ſpeak of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> not ſo much as it relates to Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> as to Matters of <hi>Practice;</hi> not how it ought to form our <hi>Judgments</hi> and model our <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,</hi> as how it ought to direct our <hi>Lives,</hi> and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern our <hi>Actions,</hi> which is much more neceſſary of the two.</p>
            <p n="1">1. WHAT is meant by <hi>Conſcience,</hi> which is almoſt in every one's Mouth, and hath created ſo much <hi>Noiſe</hi> and Buſſle in the World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſcience</hi> is that Power, or Faculty of the Mind, which judges of our Actions according to a right Rule, whether they be agreeable to it or not; or 'tis the <hi>reflex Act</hi> of our Reaſon and Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, reſpecting the Goodneſs or Badneſs of our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; ſo that <hi>Conſcience</hi> is an Act of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</hi> and but another Name for <hi>Reaſon:</hi> 'Tis <hi>Reaſon</hi> exercis'd about the Lawfulneſs, or Unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of what we do; or the Judgment of our Minds, acquitting, or condemning us in our own Thoughts.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:60769:3"/>
            <p>In which Deſcription of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> we may take Notice of theſe following things, which enter the Definition, and conſtitute the Nature of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, Conſcience</hi> ſuppoſeth a Rule by which it ought to be directed and governed in all its Actings; for <hi>Conſcience</hi> is no Lordly, nor Lawleſs Principle, and therefore is not left at Liberty to think or do what it liſt, to act raſhly, and at all Adventures. No, <hi>Conſcience</hi> is under Authority and Reſtraint, and ought to be kept within Bounds, and not ſuffered to run out into an unaccountable Extravagancy, or vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Extream; to keep its Eye daily on the <hi>Rule,</hi> and take <hi>Advice</hi> from thence in what it doth for God, whoſe <hi>Will</hi> ought to be a Law in this Caſe, and none elſe. And that, be ſure, is a Rule large enough for <hi>Conſcience</hi> to walk by; and which, together with Judgment and Diſcretion in the Application thereof, is ſufficient to direct a Chriſtian upon all occaſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> There muſt be a <hi>Knowledge</hi> of this Rule, otherwiſe <hi>Conſcience</hi> is not concern'd.</p>
            <p>The very Notion of the Word, according to the Letter and Derivation of it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>Greek,</hi> and <hi>Conſcientia</hi> in <hi>Latine</hi> imports as much. There cannot be <hi>Conſcientia</hi> without <hi>Scientia,</hi> no Conſcience with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Knowledge. If I am wholly ignorant of the Rule or Law, 'tis all one to me, as if there were none at all; and obligeth me no further than I have or may have any Knowledge or Information thereof; in this Sence, <hi>Quod non apparet, non eſt,</hi> 'Tis all one not to be, as not to appear ſo.</p>
            <p>I muſt therefore know what my Duty is, or what it is the Law requires of me, before I can think my ſelf obliged thereby; and till I know it, or have the Means of arriving at the Knowledge of it, I lie under no Obligation from thence: For a blind Man may
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60769:4"/>with as much Reaſon be oblig'd to walk ſteadily in a ſtreight Line, or narrow Path, tho he cannot ſee one Step of his way, as that a man ſhould be oblig'd in Conſcience to any <hi>Law,</hi> whereof he is totally ignorant, or deprived of the means of knowing of it. I ſpeak here of <hi>invincible,</hi> not <hi>affected</hi> Ignorance, there being as much difference between them two, as between na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and wilful Blindneſs, between a man's having no Eyes at all, and another that ſhuts them cloſe, and will not open or make uſe of them to ſee his way. The former excuſeth indeed; but the later never did, and never will. For inſtance, thoſe miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably blind <hi>Heathen,</hi> who ſit in Darkneſs, and ſee no Light, who never heard of the Name of Chriſt, nor once had the glad Tidings of Salvation preached un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them; they are not bound to believe and embrace the Goſpel under the Penalty of Damnation, as we are, who enjoy the means, and daily ſit under the joyful Sound thereof. All that they are to do, is to comply with the rational Dictates of their own Mind, and conform to that part of the Divine Law which is written upon their Hearts, and to live up to the light of natural Religion: The ground or reaſon of which <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> is taken from that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14, 15. <hi>For when the Gentiles, which have not the Law, do by Nature the things contain'd in the Law, theſe having not a Law, are a Law unto themſelves:</hi> Which ſhews the work of the Law written in their Hearts, their <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences</hi> alſo bearing them Witneſs, and their Thoughts in the mran time <hi>accuſing,</hi> or <hi>excuſing</hi> one another. Now according to this of the Apoſtle, <hi>If the Gentiles do by Nature the things contain'd in the Law,</hi> and their Conſciences thereupon excuſe and bear witneſs on their behalf (as is here expreſly affirm'd) why ſhould we be ſo uncharitable as to paſs Sentence againſt thoſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60769:4"/>who are acquitted by their own <hi>Conſciences,</hi> or think that the Great and Good God, who is the Maker of us all, will be as partial and ſevere as we are wont to be in our Cenſures of them. No, for we are told <hi>in every Nation, he that fears God, and works Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhall be accepted,</hi> Acts 10.35. This Propoſition of the Apoſtle, being, no doubt, true in every Age, as well before, as after Chriſt's Time, there being but one way of Salvation both for Jew and Gentile, and but one Mediator between God and Man, who is called <hi>the Saviour of all Men, tho' more eſpecially of ſuch as believe, i. e.</hi> of Chriſtians; no other name being given among Men, no other Mediator being conſtituted throughout the World beſide him, where by they can hope to be ſaved, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12. tho' how-and in what manner the Merit of Chriſt is applyed, unto them that have no explicite Knowledge or Faith in him, is a Myſtery too high for our Reach; and therefore, as a ſecret thing, belongs only to God.</p>
            <p>The meaning of all that hath been ſaid upon this particular, is in ſhort this, That there muſt be not only a Rule, but a Knowledge of that Rule before it can oblige <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> There is the Judgment of the Mind con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our Actions, a judging of them by a known Rule, of what Kind or Nature they are, whether good or bad, well or ill done, agreeable to the Intent of the Law or not. From whence ariſeth in the</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourth</hi> place, The giving, or paſſing Sentence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſelves, in reference to the Lawfulneſs, or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulneſs of our Actions; the acquitting, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning our ſelves in our own Breaſts, and judging of our Spiritual State; or moral Condition, whether we are able to approve our ſelves unto God, who is the ſtrict Obſerver, and ſupream Judge of all our Actions.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:60769:5"/>
            <p>And from theſe two laſt Acts reſults the Teſtimony of our Conſciences; which if it vote on our Behalf, yields us matter of Comfort in the midſt of all our Sufferings, enables us to hold up our Heads with Joy, and gives us Confidence towards God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may <hi>draw near with a true Heart, in full aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of Faith, having our Hearts ſprinkled from an Evil Aſſurance, and our Bodies waſht with pure Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> Heb. 10.22. And again, <hi>Beloved, if our Hearts</hi> (that is, our Conſciences) <hi>condemn us not, then have we Confidence towards God,</hi> 1 John 3.21.</p>
            <p>But if the Teſtimony of Conſcience make againſt us, then it cannot chuſe but afflict and diſquiet us, make our Countenances to fall, and cauſe ſad thoughts to ariſe within us; which in ſome men is attended with greater Horror than in others, according as Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is awakened, or laid to ſleep.</p>
            <p>The whole Tranſaction of <hi>Conſcience</hi> in this Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, is ſometimes repreſented by way of <hi>Syllogiſm,</hi> in three Propoſitions.</p>
            <p>That which forms the firſt <hi>Propoſition,</hi> is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: This makes Report of the Law, and draws its <hi>Medium,</hi> or Argument from thence.</p>
            <p>That which forms the <hi>Minor,</hi> is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Conſcience:</hi> This makes a particular Application of the Law, or Rule unto a Man's own ſelf, or brings it home to his own Caſe.</p>
            <p>The Third infers the <hi>Concluſion</hi> from both, and is therefore called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is the Judgment of <hi>Conſcience</hi> upon the whole; whereby a man is able to judge of his Actions, and paſs Sentence upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, either of Abſolution, or Condemnation.</p>
            <p>Having reſolved the firſt Enquiry, What <hi>Conſcience</hi> is? it will from hence more eaſily appear in the next place.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:60769:5"/>
            <p n="2">2. WHAT it is to make Conſcience of our Actions, or to live according to Conſcience.</p>
            <p>Negatively, 'Tis not to do what we liſt, to walk at large, or live at randome, 'tis not to be tranſported with Humour, or Paſſion, or Diſcontent. 'Tis not to act in Conformity to the Opinions of other Men, or of a particular Sect or Party as ſuch; no nor al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to follow the Dictates and Perſuaſions of our own prejudic'd and mis-inform'd Minds, whereof, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſome People are ſo very fond, as to make no difference between <hi>Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Prejudice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore poſitively; To act according to Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, is to walk by Rule, and live according to Law; to frame all our Actions according to the Will and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of our Maker, who hath abſolute Authority over us, and claims a greater Share in us, than we can in our ſelves: For Conſcience is under Authority, ty'd to a Rule, and muſt have a Law for its Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Governance.</p>
            <p>Now when we perform our Actions in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as may be agreeable to the Rule which is given us for the right Government thereof; and when the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Practice of our Lives bears ſome Proportion thereunto; this is to make <hi>Conſcience</hi> of our ways, and to approve our ſelves <hi>to our ſelves</hi> in ſo doing.</p>
            <p>That man therefore that hath no reſpect to the Rule of his Actions, nor takes any care to render them in ſome good meaſure anſwerable to it; ſuch a one (let his plea and pretence be never ſo ſpecious and demure) makes no <hi>Conſcience</hi> how he lives, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently can never expect the Teſtimony of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence on his ſide, much leſs be able to Rejoyce in it.</p>
            <p>Now the chief Rule or Law that is to direct <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> and govern our <hi>Actions,</hi> is the <hi>Canon</hi> of <hi>Holy
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60769:6"/>Scripture,</hi> the written Word, or reveal'd Will of God. This lays the ſtrongeſt, nay, the only Obligation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Conſcience;</hi> which can acquit us no farther, than our Actions are correſpondent to this Rule; and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which all others are ſubordinate, and may be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied.</p>
            <p>So that to live according to <hi>Conſcience,</hi> is to meaſure out our Actions by the Rule of God's Word; to conform the General Practiſe and Courſe of our Lives unto the Law of Chriſt, which is the moſt perfect Rule of Righteouſneſs, that is, or can be given us, and unto which all others ought to refer: 'Tis to live in Obedience to a Divine Command, and to ſubject our ſelves entirely to the Will and Pleaſure of him, who hath the abſolute Diſpoſe and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our <hi>Conſciences,</hi> and to whom we owe all the Duty and Service we are capable of. He that doth otherwiſe doth amiſs, and can never be able to juſtifie himſelf unto his own Mind, much leſs anſwer it to God when he cannot do it to his own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>From what hath been ſaid, it appears, that <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> is, as I ſaid before, no lawleſs or ungo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernable Principle, no prejudic'd, or diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented Paſſion, no affected, or ſuperſtitious Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as ſome would make us believe: 'Tis no Tyrannical, or Deſpotick Lord, ſo as to impoſe its own private Dictates for Divine Commands; much leſs the wild Extravagancies, and enthuſiaſtick Conceits of this or that Sect, under pretence of Religion, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Inſtances have not been wanting in this Nation and Age of ours. Conſcience is God's Subſtitute and Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent, and can act or impoſe no further than it hath Warrant or Authority from him ſo to do: To do more than this, is to exceed its Commiſſion, and to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60769:6"/>do that which all the fine Pretences in the World will never be able to bear us out in.</p>
            <p n="3">3. NOTWITHSTANDING, <hi>Conſcience,</hi> by many perſons pretending to it, hath been wretchedly Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, yet it ought not to be ſlighted, or caſt off ever the more upon that Account.</p>
            <p>Now this implies two things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> It ſuppoſeth that <hi>Conſcience</hi> may be abuſed; nay, actually hath been ſo; and that to very ill Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes: And this is too great a Truth ever to be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and which ſad Experience doth every day give us too manifeſt and undeniable a Proof of.</p>
            <p>To inſtance only in Generals; Many there are, and God knows how few amongſt us can plead <hi>Not Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> in this reſpect, who have cried up Religion, and pleaded Conſcience; yet have had no regard to the Laws of the one, or Rule of the other, who, 'tis to be fear'd, never took any pains to examine and ſearch into the Nature and Reaſon of their Actions, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were agreeable to the mind of God, or had any Command of his, to Warrant and Authorize them. Conſcience in ſuch Perſons had never regard to any Law but that of their own Paſſions and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, which hath put them upon many notorious and foul Impieties, and which have been firſt practiſed, then excuſed, and at length arrived at that heighth of Confidence, as publickly to be maintain'd and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified in the face of the whole World; and that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name and plea of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> notwithſtanding they were directly oppoſed to the common Dictates of Nature, and expreſs Laws of Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>Thus among the Heathen, <hi>Conſcience</hi> through blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſuperſtition, hath miſ-lead them to many vile, and unnatural pieces of wickedneſs; and among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, who ought to have known and done better,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60769:7"/>it hath been guilty of little leſs. The moſt Tragical Crimes that ever came upon the Stage, have been act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under this Veil, and diſguiſed with this Pretence.</p>
            <p>This it was which put <hi>Agamemnon</hi> upon ſacrificing his Daughter, and urg'd his Son <hi>Oreſtes</hi> to revenge his Father's Death in the Murder of his Mother. This mov'd the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> to the Slaughter of two 100 young Noblemen at a time, to appeaſe their ſurly God <hi>Saturn,</hi> after a notable Defeat received from their Enemies. And upon this account it became a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Practice among ſeveral Nations, to offer up their Children in Sacrifice to their Idols; which <hi>Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Heathen,</hi> as the Holy Scripture calls it, <hi>was afterward imitated by the backsliding Iſraelites, who burnt their children to</hi> Moloch, <hi>and made them paſs through the fire in the valley of</hi> Hinnon, 2 Chr. 28.3. And it was <hi>Conſcience</hi> mingled with Spite and Malice, that moved their Countrey-men in after-Ages to crucifie the Lord of Life, and put him to open Shame and Death: For, ſay they, <hi>we have a Law, and by that Law he ought to die,</hi> &amp;c. John 19.7.</p>
            <p>And well had it been, if this <hi>Abomination</hi> had been confin'd to the Heathen World, or paſt no further than the Borders of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation: But which is more to be aggravated and lamented too, Chriſtians of almoſt all Parties and Perſuaſions, have not come behind the very worſt of the <hi>Heathens,</hi> acting over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain all the Extravagancies of a <hi>Pagan</hi> Superſtition, and that for <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> ſake, if they may be believ'd.</p>
            <p>This hath created Factions, and ſown Sedition both in Church and State; invaded Kingdoms from abroad, and incited to Rebellion at home, contrived Plots, and hatch'd Conſpiracies, acted Treaſons, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Maſſacres, and abſolved Subjects from their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60769:7"/>Allegiance, and made them caſt off the Yoke of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to their Lawful Soveraigns.</p>
            <p>Whatever Miſchief or Wickedneſs is or can be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed in the Name of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and <hi>Murder, Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> or <hi>Treaſon, Ambition,</hi> and <hi>Revenge,</hi> they have all been the Dictates of ſome Mens <hi>Conſciences,</hi> and proceeded from the <hi>Oracle</hi> of a deluded and miſtaken Religion. Under this pretence ill Men have cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed their Natural <hi>Infirmities,</hi> let looſe their <hi>Paſſions,</hi> vented their Spleen, diſguiſed their Ambition, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted their own private Intereſt to the Ruine of the Publick, and carried on the worſt deſign of a Spite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Nature and Diſcontented Faction.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Conſcience</hi> in ſuch Men as theſe was <hi>Legibus Soluta,</hi> had no reſpect to <hi>Laws,</hi> unleſs it were to break and violate them, being <hi>Lawleſs,</hi> and <hi>Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient,</hi> &amp;c. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9.</p>
            <p>Such a Conſcience as this can as eaſily break all Bands, and cut in ſunder all the Cords of Obedience as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did the Cords, wherewith his <hi>Enemies</hi> had bound him: And when once the Tie of <hi>Conſcience</hi> is loos'd or broken, little hopes of their being held by any other.</p>
            <p>But we know very well, from whence the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of ſuch a <hi>Conſcience</hi> came at firſt, and what Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief and Confuſion it hath wrought in all parts of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> ever ſince. Whoever therefore is acted thereby, whether they know it, or no, yet for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain they are no better than Factours for <hi>Popery,</hi> the Tools and Engines of a <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> and the very Spawn of the <hi>Fiſherman</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> actuated by a Spirit whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Oppoſite to that of Chriſt and his Goſpel: A Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that like the Evil One is ever reſtleſs and unquiet, which hath been formerly at work, and no doubt is ſo ſtill, though like their Predeceſſors in the <hi>Powder-Plot,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:60769:8"/>they dig under ground in a more Secret and Clandeſtine manner, endeavouring not only to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Jealouſies and Diſcontents, but contriving and laying Snares to involve us in the like unnatural Guilt and <hi>Treachery</hi> with themſelves: For it is well known, the <hi>Papiſts</hi> have Leaven'd moſt of our Sects, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Mask and Diſguiſe have Oppugn'd our Church, ſow'd the Tares of Faction and Diſſention among us, and arm'd her Boſome Friends, (which are evermore the worſt of Enemies) with Weapons and Arguments to undermine and weaken her.</p>
            <p>And really when I conſider the great Impoſture of that Corrupt Church, and the vaſt numbers that have been craftily ſeduc'd and miſlead by her, who under the Plea of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and Out-cry of Religion have acted ſo many Barbarous and unhumane Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, 'tis enough (methinks) to make a Serious Man to forſwear all <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and for ever Abjure all thoughts of Religion, were he not very well aſſured of the <hi>Abuſe</hi> of the one and <hi>Innocence</hi> of the other, and how none but the very worſt of Men have made thoſe Holy Pretences a Retreat for their Wicked and Abominable Practices.</p>
            <p>Good God! That any who pretend to <hi>Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> and not only ſo, but to <hi>Conſcience</hi> in its greateſt Strictneſs, and to <hi>Religion</hi> in its higheſt Purity, ſhould yet ſo notoriouſly abuſe the one, proſtitute the other, and act in Contradiction to both. If this be to make <hi>Conſcience</hi> of our Actions, it is in ſuch a manner as no Good Man would be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of; and if this be <hi>Religion,</hi> I plainly declare, I have none of this kind, and do heartily wiſh I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver may.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and conſequently <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> is the Refuge of Treaſon, and Sanctuary of Rebellion, if
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60769:8"/>the Holy Jeſus came (as one would think by ſome Mens Practices he did) to Sanctifie Murder, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonize thoſe Men whoſe hands are full of Bloud, to Licence Sacriledge and Sedition, or Legitimate the moſt leud and Infamous Impieties, I ſhould chuſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be a Diſciple of Honeſt <hi>Socrates,</hi> and content my ſelf to be virtuous at the rate of a Heathen, than according to the Meaſures of ſuch a Religion.</p>
            <p>But bleſſed be God, we know better things, and have been taught quite otherwiſe, we have not thus learned Chriſt; his Religion is Pure Religion and Undefiled; his Commands are Holy, Juſt, and Good; he countenanceth no ſort of Immorality, but encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageth the Univerſal Practice of all Virtue. It threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens Damnation to ſuch as reſiſt Authority, which is <hi>the Ordinance of God,</hi> and affirms the Damnation of thoſe Men to be juſt, who <hi>think to do evil, that good may come of it.</hi> Rom. 3.8. It makes it as neceſſary for Subjects to ſubmit (I do not ſay always to Obey) but to ſubmit to their Governors, as for Children to be Obedient to their Parents, and for Servants to be ſubject to their Maſters; and he that goes about to take off the Obligation of the one, may upon the ſame terms take away all Duty in Children towards Parents, and all Faithfulneſs in Servants towards Maſters: For Obedience and Subjection to Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, is as Natural and Sacred, as that which is exercis'd in Families, and kept up in a Man's own Houſe.</p>
            <p>I have inſiſted the longer on this, not ſo much to look backward as forward; to undeceive people by opening their Eyes and diſcovering thoſe <hi>Pious Frauds, Profane Cheats,</hi> and <hi>Hypocritical Abuſes,</hi> which for a long time hath paſt cleverly with ſome Men, under
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60769:9"/>the Notion of <hi>Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Religion;</hi> and to ſhew you what Spirit ſuch Men are of, thereby to Caution you for the future againſt all ſuch leud <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Pretences,</hi> how ſpeciouſly ſoever they may be gilded over, and that <hi>you take heed, that</hi> you ſuffer not your ſelves to be cheated out of a <hi>Peaceable, Loyal,</hi> and <hi>Well-temper'd</hi> Religion, by any bold Incendiary or cunning Hypocrite of them all, be they of what <hi>Party</hi> or <hi>Faction</hi> they will, whether <hi>Foreign</hi> or <hi>Domeſtick,</hi> at Home or Abroad. But yet in the</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Second</hi> place, Notwithſtanding <hi>Conſcience</hi> hath been ſo groſly miſtaken and abuſed; yet it ought not to be ſlighted, much leſs caſt off upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, any more than Religion which hath often met with the like hard Fate, or Civil Government which hath been Uſurp'd by thoſe that had no Right to it, and manag'd quite contrary to the <hi>Primitive End</hi> and <hi>Inſtitution</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p>Now if the Abuſes of <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> be not a ſufficient Reaſon for our rejecting of them, no more is it for the laying aſide of <hi>Conſcience.</hi> Becauſe the greateſt Abuſe can never be made an Argument for the Total <hi>Abandoning</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p>For if you come once to caſt off <hi>Conſcience,</hi> you throw off with it all Obligation to Duty, you take away all Senſe of <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Evil,</hi> all Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Virtue</hi> and <hi>Vice, Right</hi> and <hi>Wrong,</hi> and thereby reduce <hi>Mankind</hi> into the Rank of <hi>Brute-beaſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Without regard to <hi>Conſcience</hi> you are not capable of <hi>Religion,</hi> nor of the ordinary Duties of <hi>Morality,</hi> we cannot do one good Action without it, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the Witneſs and Teſtimony thereof.</p>
            <p>There will be then no peace in <hi>Private Families,</hi> nor good Government in <hi>Publick Societies;</hi> no Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Magiſtrates nor Subjection to Authority.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60769:9"/>No Man then will either Fear God or Honour the King; or do their Duty one toward another, all which are yet enjoyn'd and bound expreſsly upon our <hi>Conſciences,</hi> by the Holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſcience</hi> then is uſeful and neceſſary in that it implys an Obligation to Duty, and lays upon us the ſtrongeſt Bonds of Obedience. There is no Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or <hi>Perſwaſive</hi> like it: It is ſtronger than all our little Hopes and Fears in this World; 'tis not to be compell'd by force, nor brib'd by <hi>Intereſt,</hi> nor fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all the Terrors and Apprehenſions of Death and the Grave. Inſomuch, as <hi>Conſcience,</hi> though daily abuſed by ill Men to ill deſigns, is yet of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent uſe, where rightly inform'd, duly apply'd, and carefully heeded and attended unto. Where it is Reverenc'd and regarded as it ought, it tends mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the making Men throughly Good and Virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Juſt in their <hi>Pretences,</hi> Honeſt in their <hi>Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> Upright and Sincere in all their <hi>Promiſes</hi> and <hi>Profeſſions;</hi> all which, where Men make no Scruple of any thing, muſt needs be Falſe, Diſſembling, and Treacherous.</p>
            <p>Where Men are willing to exerciſe a good <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> or keep it void of Offence, they will not put Tricks and Cheats upon themſelves or others, they will not go about to mock God and deceive their own Souls, they will ſcorn to do an ill Action and afterwards colour it over with a plauſible Excuſe or Hypocritical Evaſion. But will endeavour after the practice of unfeignee Goodneſs, a hearty Compliance with their whole <hi>Duty,</hi> having their <hi>Converſation,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>In</hi> Simplicity <hi>and</hi> Godly Sincerity, <hi>and not with Fleſhly Wiſdom.</hi> 2 Cor. 1.12. In a word, he will ſtrive to approve himſelf to God as well as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60769:10"/>Man, and to Man as well as God; that he may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as good as poſſibly he can, that is, as the Grace of God and his own honeſt endeavors will enable him to be.</p>
            <p>That Man therefore, that makes no <hi>Conſcience</hi> of any thing he does or ſays, can never become ſo good as he ought; He can be no true and laſting Friend either to Church or State, to his King or Countrey, and conſequently unſafe to be truſted by either; but he that ſhall go about to <hi>Debauch</hi> and <hi>Proſtitute</hi> his <hi>Conſcience,</hi> is of all others the very worſt, and no Sinner to the <hi>Conſcientious</hi> Sinner, who can ſin with a good <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and do Evil that Good may come of it, whoſe <hi>Damnation</hi> as it is moſt juſt, ſo their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming is moſt difficult, as being obſtinate in their <hi>Prejudices</hi> againſt every thing, that is or can be offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for their Conviction.</p>
            <p>And thus you ſee the great Uſe and Neceſſity of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> where it is regarded and valued as it ought, and therefore is not to be decry'd, for the ill uſe made thereof: For to caſt off <hi>Conſcience</hi> is in effect to caſt off all Religion With it; to Baniſh all true Goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſs, Common Honeſty, and Moral Virtue out of the World, and conſequently all that Order, Pence, Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Civil Society, which reſults from thence, and wherein the Happineſs of this Life doth chiefly conſiſt.</p>
            <p>I PROCEED now in the <hi>Fourth</hi> place, to ſhew in or about what things <hi>Conſcience</hi> ought principally to be concern'd or exerciſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> For the better underſtanding of which, I muſt remind you a little of what I have already hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the deſcription of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> namely, that <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> preſuppoſeth a Rule or Law; and therefore is not particularly concern'd about things <hi>Indifferent</hi> as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60769:10"/>ſuch, which come within the compaſs of no Rule, nor within the Limits of any Command or Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For <hi>Conſcience</hi> is no further concern'd about any thing or action, than as 'tis an Inſtance of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to, or Tranſgreſſion of a Law; now where there is no <hi>Law,</hi> there is no <hi>Tranſgreſſion,</hi> no nor <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> neither.</p>
            <p>Now the things we call Indifferent are ſuch as God hath given no particular Command either for or againſt, and upon that account become of a Middle nature be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Good and Evil, as being neither commanded nor forbidden; if therefore not commanded, they do not oblige <hi>Conſcience</hi> in point of Obedience; if not forbidden they offend not <hi>Conſcience</hi> in point of Guilt.</p>
            <p>This is the true and eaſie Notion of things <hi>Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,</hi> as coming under no immediate Injunction or Prohibition, and therefore left free as to the Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance or Omiſſion, unleſs Prudence ſhall otherwiſe direct or lawful Authority interpoſe.</p>
            <p>But ſome there are, who will admit nothing for Indifferent, but what Scripture doth expreſly war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and affirm to be ſo; but then there can be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing call'd Indifferent in the World, becauſe there is no Text throughout the whole Bible, that ſpeaks any thing to this purpoſe, or makes mention of what is Indifferent and what not; And yet that ſome things in or about Religion are indifferent, and may be done or not done without Sin, we have the general conſent of moſt of our Reformed <hi>Divines;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Calv. Beza, Bucer, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la. P. Martyr</hi> cum pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis aliis, quos om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merare jam taederet.</note> and that as well of Foreign Churches as of our own.</p>
            <p>'Tis therefore ſufficient warrant for me to judge any thing indifferent, whereof the Scripture is wholly ſilent and makes no mention at all, either one way or other, as in Matters of External <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:60769:11"/>the Outward Modes and Circumſtances of <hi>Divine</hi> Worſhip, which are all of them, of an indifferent Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and wherein there is no Religion or Sin at all, as conſider'd abſolutely in themſelves, and ſtript of all other Circumſtances, which may alter the caſe.</p>
            <p>Indifferent things therefore being neither good nor evil in themſelves, may be done, or not done, without ſinning againſt God, or offending <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when theſe things, which are indifferent in their own Nature, do either tend to, or come under the General Rules of Order and Decency, and have withal the Addition of lawful Authority to re-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them; then the Practice of them becomes not only lawful, but in that reſpect neceſſary, tho' they remain ſtill indifferent as to their own Nature. I ſay, tho' the Nature of them is not changed by the <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>addition</hi> of lawful Authority, but remain indifferent as before, yet the Practice of them is no longer ſo; but becomes a neceſſary Inſtance of our Obedience; and therefore Obſtinacy in refuſing to comply with ſuch Injunctions, cannot excuſe from Guilt, except it could be proved, <hi>That Diſobedience to the lawful com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the Magiſtrate is no Sin, and the ſtudy of the Churches Peace and Quiet is no Duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the clearer Illuſtration of this, I ſhall inſtance but in one Ceremony at preſent, which by many is ſcrupled at; but, I think, without any Ground, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from <hi>Scripture,</hi> or <hi>Reaſon;</hi> and that is, <hi>Kneeling</hi> at the Bleſſed <hi>Sacrament,</hi> which is the only Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that is enjoyn'd or requir'd from the Layety in the Communion of our Church. 'Tis impoſſible we ſhould receive the Holy <hi>Sacrament</hi> without ſome Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture which is natural to every Action, whether it be <hi>Sitting, Standing, Kneeling,</hi> or <hi>Leaning, i. e.</hi> incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Body on one ſide, which is generally thought
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60769:11"/>to be the Poſture of our Saviour and his Diſciples, at the firſt Inſtitution thereof, according to the Cuſtom of the <hi>Eaſt.</hi> Each of theſe Poſtures conſidered in themſelves are equally indifferent, and one to be ſcrupled no more than another, becauſe they are all of them natural to bodily Action. <hi>Kneeling</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the <hi>Firſt</hi> place being not forbidden in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is no more unlawful than <hi>Sitting</hi> or <hi>Standing;</hi> and being a natural Geſture of the Body, is as indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent as any of the reſt: But then <hi>Secondly,</hi> as it is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Poſture, and expreſſive of greater Reverence and Humility than that of Sitting or Standing; ſo it may be preferr'd as more convenient and ſuitable to the Piety and Devotion of that <hi>Holy Ordinance,</hi> than any other Geſture.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As 'tis enjoyn'd by the Authority and Governours of the Church (whoſe Power in things of this Nature, ſome men are unwilling to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand) ſo it becomes more neceſſary and binding as to the Uſe thereof: What was indifferent before in one reſpect, becomes convenient in another, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in a third: 'Tis <hi>indifferent</hi> in its own nature, becauſe not forbidden: 'Tis <hi>convenient,</hi> in regard of its natural Significancy, as <hi>betokening</hi> more Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and Devotion; and 'tis neceſſary, in reſpect of the Command of our Governours, as an Inſtance of our Obedience to them, which God hath made our Duty, and that for <hi>Conſcience</hi> ſake.</p>
            <p>That Action therefore which is natural and indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, convenient and reverent, and upon thoſe Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts commanded and enjoyned; I would fain know where doth the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawfulneſs</hi> of it lie, or where is the <hi>Sin</hi> of ſuch an Action to be found?</p>
            <p>They therefore that ſhall ſcruple Kneeling at the S. Sacrament, eſpecially ſince our Church hath aſſured
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60769:12"/>them, that there is no intention of adoring the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or the ſuppoſed Preſence of Chriſt's Body, I fear, underſtand not, what Reverence and Devotion is, ſo well as they ought; but diſcover ſomething of a Temper, which if left looſe, would be troubleſome and uneaſie under all Government and Diſcipline, tho' never ſo ſo <hi>pure</hi> and <hi>primitive,</hi> notwithſtanding they ſeem ſuch Zealous Contenders for it.</p>
            <p>But pray, why ſhould a Lawful Authority be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, for doing that which particular Men, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Teachers do daily practiſe in their ſeveral Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and Illegal Aſſembles, namely, impoſing upon the <hi>Conſciences</hi> of Men, and requiring their Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſeveral things, which they have no expreſs Rule for in Scripture, and yet make this the great Objection againſt the Worſhip and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of our Church; in which reſpect they are no leſs <hi>Magiſterial,</hi> if not more, than our Governors, whom upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions they Arraign <hi>as ſuch;</hi> for without any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from God or the Magiſtrate, they exerciſe an <hi>Arbitrary Dominion</hi> over the <hi>Conſciences</hi> of thoſe Men, who have weakneſs enough to liſt themſelves into their <hi>Party:</hi> They take away the nature of things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and make ſome things neceſſary, which were not ſo before, and ſome things they can diſpenſe withal as indifferent, which are neceſſarily required, to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnaring of Peoples <hi>Conſciences,</hi> who otherwiſe it may be, mean well, and are too honeſt to ſuſpect the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of their deſigns, as I might inſtance both in the Claſſical and Congregational way: Whereas our Church never pretended to alter the nature of things, either neceſſary and eſſential to Religion, or only ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidental and indifferent, but leaves them as they are: She only directs the Practice of them ſo far as they tend to <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Decency,</hi> are expreſſive of <hi>Reverence</hi> and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60769:12"/>
               <hi>Devoition,</hi> and become a proof of <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,</hi> to lawful Authority; a <hi>Duty</hi> which I cannot think ſo meanly of as ſome do, conſidering how pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorily it is enjoined by the Holy Ghoſt in many places of the Goſpel, and the great <hi>Influence</hi> it hath upon the Peace of the Church and Security of the Government, under which we live.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, Conſcience</hi> I told you includes Knowledge as much in the Notion of the thing, as Compoſition of the word; where there is no Knowledge, there can be no <hi>Conſcience,</hi> becauſe in ſuch a caſe it is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to do, or how to govern it ſelf and judge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right; whereupon <hi>Conſcience</hi> is not ſo much concern'd about things that are uncertain, whereof we can have no ſure Proof or clear Evidence, either from Senſe Reaſon, or Revelation, which are the three only ways of attaining Knowledge, or arriving at the certainty of any thing.</p>
            <p>Thus in matters of School Queſtion or Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſial Divinity, which are banded to and fro with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable Arguments on both ſides: For Inſtance, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther The Fire in Hell be Material or Metaphorical, true In the <hi>Letter</hi> or in a <hi>Figure,</hi> ſo we do but believe there is ſuch a place as Hell reſerved for the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Wicked Men, as Scripture doth aſſure us, <hi>Conſcience,</hi> as to the reſt, is not concern'd to believe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther one way or other; becauſe Scripture is ſilent in the caſe, and the Arguments from Reaſon on either hand are alike probable; and if I am induc'd to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve one part of the Queſtion rather than the other, this can ariſe no higher, than to a private Opinion of my own, not a publick Article of my <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi> wherein my private Judgment not my <hi>Conſcience</hi> is concern'd. That Chriſt was born of a Pure Virgin is
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60769:13"/>matter of Faith, and <hi>conſequently</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, becauſe Scripture doth affirm it; but whether ſhe remain'd ſo all her Life long, is not ſo: Indeed it hath been an Opinion in the Church, that ſhe did, but however there is no other Argument but that of <hi>Piè Credimus,</hi> that can induce us to be of that mind.</p>
            <p>In like manner the Deſcent of Chriſt into Hell, ſo we do not deny the thing, which hath for many Ages been a received Article of the Apoſtles Creed, tho left out in ſome others, it matters not greatly, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were <hi>Local</hi> or <hi>Virtual, Metaphorical,</hi> or <hi>Metony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical:</hi> for in all theſe ſeveral Senſes it hath been taken by Learned and Pious Men; but in which of theſe we need not be overmuch concern'd; for this Article be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not expreſly Revealed, or clearly delivered in Scripture, we believe it chiefly upon the account of the Apoſtles Creed, whoſe Antiquity ought to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand our <hi>Reverence</hi> and <hi>Reſpect,</hi> tho I think it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtrictly oblige my <hi>Conſcience;</hi> eſpecially when the Church hath not determin'd any thing in the Caſe (any more than Scripture) but left me at Liberty to judge either way as I ſee cauſe. The like may be ſaid of the Knowledge of the Saints departed, with many others, which for Brevity ſake I now omit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Some things there are, tho for certain Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, yet being <hi>Obſcure</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nintelligible</hi> in their own nature, cannt ſo immediately oblige our <hi>Conſciences,</hi> as thoſe that are more <hi>plain</hi> and <hi>Obvious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Decrees</hi> of God, <hi>Arcana</hi> of <hi>Providence,</hi> the great and Stupendous <hi>Myſtery</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed Trinity,</hi> and <hi>Incomprehenſible <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of the Two Natures in the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> theſe are, in many things, above our Reach and Capacity, and ſo far as they are above us, belong not to us. A modeſt and humble Faith is here requiſite, and all that is expected from the common
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60769:13"/>and ordinary ſort of <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> a too curious ſearch and inquiry into theſe Venerable Myſteries being not <hi>conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> for all, nor <hi>abſolutely neceſſary</hi> for any.</p>
            <p>A particular Explication of them, concerns my Faith no further than as it is conſonant to Sacred Scripture, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to what is more plainly revealed in Holy Writ; or elſe by natural and genuine Conſequence, may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced there-from.</p>
            <p>But now, as for other Difficulties that may ariſe from thence, I am not bound to pin my Faith on any one man's Sleeve, nor receive his <hi>Scheme,</hi> or <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for <hi>inſpir'd Doctrine:</hi> No, nor for <hi>Truth</hi> neither, any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than he can confirm it by Scripture, which is the ſole infallible Teſt of Divine Truth: All that in this Caſe I am oblig'd to do, is to guide my <hi>Conſcience</hi> by <hi>Scripture,</hi> and my <hi>Judgment</hi> by the <hi>catholick Determinations</hi> of the Church, that is, I am oblig'd in Conſcience to believe all that the Scripture reveals, and make that the Rule of my Faith and Obedience: But in all other things where dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties may ariſe, and Scripture is either totally ſilent, or very obſcure, here we ought to believe as the Church believes; miſtake me not, I do not ſpeak it in a Popiſh Sence, which ſets up the <hi>Traditien</hi> of the Church in Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to <hi>Scripture;</hi> and in an impious manner, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers them before it, teaching for Doctrines the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Men; but my meaning is, that I, and every bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy elſe, in matters dubious and obſcure, ought to be ſo modeſt as to miſtruſt our own particular Judgments, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than that of the Church, and ſubmit our <hi>Private</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions to her <hi>Publick</hi> Determinations. If not, yet the <hi>leaſt</hi> that in this Caſe we ought to do, is to keep our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion to our ſelves, rather than diſturb the Peace, or oppoſe the received Doctrine of the Church, out of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreet Zeal for any fond or affected Opinion of our own. For pray conſider, Can it be any other than Pride, or Self-conceit, to call it no worſe, for a few private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60769:14"/>to oppoſe their particular <hi>Sentiments</hi> to the <hi>Catholick Faith,</hi> and what they decry in their Governors to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe more unjuſtly themſelves, by <hi>Preſcribing</hi> to their Superiors in Matters dubious and uncertain, and which are perpetually controverted on all hands?</p>
            <p>In all things of this nature <hi>Conſcience</hi> obligeth me to be Humble and Modeſt rather than Poſitive and Peremptory; and therefore it would better become us to receive our Faith <hi>from,</hi> than impoſe ours <hi>upon</hi> the Church in whoſe Communion we live, and of the Truth of whoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine we are ſatisfied in the main, as the <hi>Diſſenting Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> are generally with ours. But however, if they ſee Reaſon to <hi>Diſſent</hi> in their private Thoughts from the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht Faith, they ought to keep their Judgment to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and not diſturb her Peace on that account: In this Senſe let them remember that of the Apoſtle, <hi>He that hath Faith, let him have it to himſelf. And he that keeps it there, way keep it ſafe enough, and out of the reach of all Humane Power and Compulſion.</hi> For <hi>Conſcience,</hi> while it keeps with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in its due bounds cannot, ought not, to be compell'd by any Power upon Earth; for in that reſpect it is free, and never to be fore't.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Secondly,</hi> and poſitively, <hi>Conſcience</hi> is chiefly and more immediately concern'd about ſuch things as are more <hi>neceſſary</hi> and <hi>ſubſtantial, plain</hi> and <hi>obvious</hi> in <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And theſe in the <hi>Firſt</hi> place are the Main <hi>Fundamental</hi> Articles of our <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi> which conſtitute the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of our <hi>Creed,</hi> and have an immediate <hi>influence</hi> on our Lives, and they are thoſe that are contain'd in our ſeveral Creeds, which are the brief Summary of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain Doctrine,</hi> and comprehenſive of the moſt Material Articles of our Belief.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Secondly,</hi> Matters of <hi>Practice,</hi> which are leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted than Matters of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and are agreed unto on all hands, and to which all the Articles of our Faith ought to refer, and are no further neceſſary than they do
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60769:14"/>ſo: For all <hi>Notions and Opinions</hi> are but things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in themſelves; it matters not whether they be true or falſe, if they paſs no further than the Brain, and are of no other uſe than to gratifie a <hi>Muſing Genius</hi> and <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culative Fancy.</hi> For to what purpoſe is the Belief of a God, if we live without him in the World? But they are of great Moment and Concern in relation to Practice; ſo far as they paſs from the Head to the Heart and have an <hi>Influence</hi> upon our Lives: Truth therefore is valuable and ought to be highly priz'd, becauſe of its near Relation to Virtue and Goodneſs, and <hi>Errour</hi> to be ſhunn'd and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided in regard of its vicious Contagion, and the ill ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect it hath upon our Morals.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſcience</hi> therefore is concern'd principally about ſuch things in <hi>Religion</hi> as are ſolid and ſubſtantial, plain and evident, neceſſary to be done, certain and eaſie to be known; and ſuch, for the moſt part, are the <hi>Agenda</hi> or Matters of Practice, which take in all the <hi>Inſtances</hi> of our Duty toward God and Man, and branch themſelves forth into the great Commands of <hi>leading a Godly, Righteous, and Sober Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the more Ignorant ſort of People, and ſuch as are Weak in the Faith, we ſhould preſs upon them the great and neceſſary Duties of Religion and Morality, ſuch as the Fear of God, Loyalty to their King, Love to their Neighbour, Honeſty in their Dealings, Temperance and Sobriety towards themſelves, A Thankful uſe and ackno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of Mercies, and a Patient-Bearing and Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Affliction. Theſe we ought daily to preſs upon our People, rather than amuſe them with Curious Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or receive them to doubtful Diſputations which oft ſtagger more than they confirm, and ſhake their Faith inſtead of ſettling it: And tho the Apoſtle bids us, <hi>Prove all things and hold faſt that which is good,</hi> Theſſal. 5.21. Yet this is not ſpoken to all indifferently; it belongs not to the Ordinary and leſſ knowing of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60769:15"/>are uſually uncapable of ſuch an Inquiry, but to ſuch who have <hi>Leiſure</hi> and <hi>Opportunity</hi> to make the Tryal, <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Skill,</hi> to go through with it, or to do it to better purpoſe, and with leſs danger to themſelves and others: But for the Generality of People, where they are ſatisfied, that no <hi>Sin</hi> is impoſed on their Practice, nor dangerous <hi>Errour</hi> on their Belief, where they have the means of Grace and <hi>Salvation</hi> afforded them, conſtant <hi>Hours</hi> of <hi>Devotion,</hi> and ſtated Times of Publick Worſhip, where they have the Liberty and <hi>Encouragement</hi> to be as <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Devout</hi> as they will, as Virtuous and <hi>Strict</hi> in their <hi>Morals</hi> as they pleaſe themſelves; In this caſe, (which God be praiſed is ours) People ought to reſt ſatisfied in the <hi>Communion</hi> of ſuch a Church, without troubling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with needleſs <hi>Scruples,</hi> uncomfortable <hi>Dolbts,</hi> or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious <hi>Curioſities,</hi> which are apt to take up too much of their Time and Thoughts, that might be better em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in the Practice of well known and neceſſary Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and improving themſelves in the happy Progreſs of a good and vertuous Life: And if <hi>ſuch</hi> a Church will not ſatisfie them, I know not (all things conſidered) where they can find a better: For no Church under the Sun is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely perfect and free from corruptions and defects; nor can ever hope to be ſo, as long as it is made up of Men, that is, of Perſons frail and fallible, and of like Paſſions and Infirmities with the reſt of the World; tho' I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this Church of ours hath <hi>as few</hi> of them as any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther under the Cope of Heaven: Nay, I ſhould not miſtake if I ſaid <hi>much fewer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſcience</hi> then is more to be heeded in reference to our Actings than Opinions; and 'tis more ſafe and eaſie to govern our Acions in reſpect of Practice, than to chufe for our ſelves in point of Doctrine. If a man holds no Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that is prejudicial to <hi>Holiaeſs</hi> and <hi>a good Life,</hi> he need not be much troubled about other things that are too high for him, and above his Reach, I dare adventure
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60769:15"/>to ſay, 'tis ſafer for him to err with Modeſty and Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, out of Love to the Churches Peace, and in ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to its Authority, than to be ſound and orthodox in his Judgment, and withal, of a ſtubbom, refractory, and contentious Spirit: And a humble, modeſt, peaceable-minded Man is more acceptable with his Errors and Fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in Judgment, than a proud and obſtinate perſon, tho' he chance to have Truth on his Side: Therefore accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the common uſe and acceptation of the Word, he is lookt upon as moſt <hi>Conſcientious,</hi> who lives beſt, and not who knows moſt; who is juſt and honeſt in his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, not who is ſound and right in his Apprehenſions. He that lives well, tho' he knows not very much, hath more of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> than he that knows more, and yet lives a great deal worſe: For <hi>Conſcience</hi> is not ſo much a <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culative,</hi> as <hi>Practical</hi> thing; and many times there is more of it found among the ſimple, honeſt, and well-meaning fort of Chriſtians, than among the more deeply learned, and profound <hi>Speculati.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſhows the too great folly and perverſeneſs; of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our People, who ſeem to be eaten up with <hi>Zeal,</hi> and plead <hi>Conſcience</hi> in thoſe things which they do not well underſtand, and it may be never will; whereas a Meek, Humble, and Teachable Spirit would better become them, and tend much more to their own Praiſe, and the Churches Peace; and be more agreeable to the Rules of the Goſpel, and the great Ends of Religion: For they may ſooner hope to be the one than the other, that is, they may become Humble and Meek, when they cannot be skill'd in all the points of Religion, or matters controverted, and under diſpute.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſcience</hi> then is moſt properly exerciſed about the more plain and neceſſary Duties of Religion, namely, matters of Practice, and ſuch Doctrines as tend more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately toward the <hi>leading of a godly, righteous, and ſober Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus have I done with the fourth General Head,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60769:16"/>and which I chiefly intended in the drawing up of this Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>It remains now, that in the</p>
            <p>5th. AND laſt place, to offer a few things by way of <hi>Advice</hi> concerning the well-governing our ſelves with relation to our <hi>Conſciences;</hi> and the</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt</hi> is this, That you be very careful to get <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> rightly informed, and well inſtructed, that you may arrive at a clear and diſtinct Apprehenſion of your Duty in all Capacities, and under all Relations whatever and <hi>Do this</hi> with all the Faithfulneſs and impartiality in the world, being ſway'd by paſſion, byaſs'd by Intereſt, and carried away with prejudice as little as may be.</p>
            <p>Labour to know, and be Inſtructed in the Truth for <hi>Truths-ſake,</hi> not ſo much to ſet your Head, as your Heart Right, not to furniſh you with matter or Talk and Diſpute, which evermore engenders <hi>Strife</hi> and <hi>Envy;</hi> but to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand your Duty, in order to the faithful practice and performance of it. Now this you muſt do, before you can ſafely follow the Dictates of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> or relie upon the Teſtimony thereof. In order hereunto, you ought to conſider the Nature and Extent of the Rule, by which <hi>Conſcience</hi> is to be govern'd and directed in all her Actions and Undertakings; and this, I told you, is the <hi>Word of God,</hi> which, laying aſide all prejudice and partiality, you ought diligently to <hi>take heed,</hi> and <hi>attend</hi> unto; and where Doubts and Difficulties may ariſe, to conſult and adviſe with your <hi>Teachers,</hi> whom God hath ſet over you, or with any other whom you have reaſon to judge moſt eminent for their Piety, Learning, Prudence and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity: to beg their Aſſiſtance, and receive their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, with that Modeſty and Reſpect as becomes <hi>Learners</hi> and <hi>Diſciples,</hi> who deſire nothing more than to <hi>come to the Knowledge of the Truth, that they might be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For want of this Care <hi>Conscience</hi> hath been ſtrangely
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60769:16"/>miſted, and run it ſelf into many groſs Errors, and foul Miſtakes. Thus many have been prompted to very ill things, one while by Paſſion, another while by Prejudice, and a third, by a corrupt and ſelf-Intereſt; and yet have thought they have been led by <hi>Zeal,</hi> and acted by <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> all the while, when, as upon ſtrict enquiry, they have found their <hi>Zeal</hi> was not according to Knowledge, and what they call'd <hi>Conſcience,</hi> in no wiſe agreeable to the Rules of their Religion. For the avoiding of which, we ſhould endeavour as much as in us lies, to get our <hi>Conſciences</hi> well inform'd, and to uſe the means in order thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> If you would have <hi>Conſcience</hi> to be rightly inform'd, you muſt endeavour after a humble, meek, and teacheable Spirit: <hi>For it is ſaid, the meek will he guide in Judgment, and the week he will teach his way,</hi> Pſalm 25.9. And it is ſaid, <hi>God reſiſts the proud, but gives Grace to the humble,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.5.</p>
            <p>Now the meek and humble ſtand higheſt in Gods Grace and Favour; and therefore more likely to be made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with his Mind and Will: Nay, they are natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moſt capable of Inſtruction, and beſt fitted for it, as being moſt deſirous to know their Duty, and ſubmit to it when they have done.</p>
            <p>Whereas on the other hand, Pride, and Paſſion, and Self-conceit, are apt to puff men up, prejudice them againſt theTruth, and fill them with Scorn and Contempt of the beſt Counſel and Advice in the World. A peeviſh and froward Diſpoſition, makes men impatient of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, and to mis-judge every thing that thwarts their particular Sentiments, inſomuch as the beſt Advice is commonly loſt and thrown away upon ſuch <hi>perverſe</hi> Tempers, tho' offered in never ſo kind and charitable a Manner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> After <hi>Conſcience</hi> is <hi>well</hi> inform'd, keep it cloſe to its Rule, and do not ſuffer it wilfully or wantonly
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60769:17"/>to ſwerve from it upon any account, or under any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence whatever, otherwiſe it may be in danger to ſeduce and deceive.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſcience</hi> is chiefly exerciſed about <hi>good</hi> or <hi>evil,</hi> the doing of the one, and the avoiding of the other. Now, tho' the Word of God is the great Standing Rule, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to which we ought to take our principal Meaſures of good and evil; yet this difference is more early taught us by the Light of Nature, and the Suggeſtion of our own Minds; and therefore whatever appears a Sin, or is uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally condemn'd for ſuch, by that Law, <hi>Conſcience</hi> muſt needs judge it to be a Sin too, and believe it condemn'd likewiſe by the Word of God: For no natural (or rather <hi>unnatural</hi>) Crime can poſſibly commence a religious Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and to think otherwiſe, is to lie under one of the groſſeſt Deluſions, and ſcandalous Miſtakes: For here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we ſet the two Laws, to wit, that of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velatron</hi> in oppoſition to one another; yea, we make them abſolutely inconſiſtent and contradictory, tho' both of them at firſt came from God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſcience</hi> therefore ought not to plead for, or encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the Practice of any Sin, namely which appears to be ſo by the Light of Nature, as well as Religion; and therefore all Treaſons and Rebellions, Murders, and Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies, Sacrilege and Perjury are great Sins, and ſuch as are diſcern'd to be ſo by natural Light; and therefore can never become otherwiſe, however they may be palli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, or pleaded for: Never think that the Plea of <hi>Conſcience, Religion,</hi> or <hi>Reformation,</hi> can juſtifie a wicked or immoral Action, ſuch as Rebellion and Perjury, which all Mankind doth naturally acknowledge and condemn for ſuch.</p>
            <p>Now every man almoſt hath ſo much of the Law of Nature yet left within him, as to diſcern the great Evil of ſuch things, tho' not always to <hi>ſhun,</hi> yet to <hi>condemn</hi> the Guilt thereof.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:60769:17"/>
            <p>What ever Nature tells us is a Sin, <hi>Conscience</hi> for that very reaſon muſt diſapprove of it too, becauſe the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of Chriſt is but the Law of Nature perfected and improved; and therefore no pretence of <hi>Conſcience</hi> drawn from Scripture can make that to be lawful, or ceaſe to be a Sin which was ſo before. Now if God's Law obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth not to Sin, much leſs the private Dictates, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> which ought evermore to make that her Rule, and fetch all her Directions from thence.</p>
            <p>For a man therefore to allow himſelf in the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch <hi>crimes</hi> as all Laws and Religions in the World muſt needs condemn as impious and wicked, pray what <hi>Conſcience</hi> hath ſuch a Man? But then to <hi>plead Conſcience</hi> in favour of ſuch things is ſo much the worſe ſtill, and renders his Crime infinitely more wicked and abominable. Such a man is never to be excuſed in what he doth of this nature: For his Excuſe, inſtead of extenuating, doth but adde to his Guilt, and mightily aggravate the Hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſneſs thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That, while I am pleading for <hi>Conſcience,</hi> I may impartially diſcharge my own, <hi>Conſcience</hi> ought not to be ſeparate from <hi>Charity,</hi> any more than from <hi>Truth. Love, Charity</hi> and <hi>Good-will,</hi> are the chief <hi>Goſpel-Precepts</hi> and <hi>Standing Principles</hi> of Chriſt's Religion: And all <hi>Zeal</hi> for the Church or State; Nay, for the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in general, or reformed Religion in particular, if void of Charity, is little worth. Charity, I mean, not only for thoſe of our own Communion, but even towards them that differ from us: For ſo far as they do it purely on the account of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and no otherwiſe, we ought to retain ſome Charity for them, be they of what Church or Communion they will.</p>
            <p>Indeed where <hi>Conſcience</hi> is <hi>manifeſtly</hi> abuſed, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries them to any thing that is wicked and unlawful; where any Sin or Immorality is countenanc'd or encouraged, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Notion or Plea of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> there we muſt leave
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60769:18"/>them, and deſervedly too, to the Publick <hi>Cenſures</hi> of the Church, and <hi>Puniſhment</hi> of the State: but where 'tis mere <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and not <hi>Faction</hi> or <hi>Peeviſhneſs</hi> that makes the Difference, there our Charity is as much due to them, as it is owing from them to us upon the like occaſion: For in this caſe there is but one <hi>Rule</hi> for them and us to walk and judge by.</p>
            <p>Therefore let a man be never ſo much in the right; let his <hi>Zeal</hi> for Truth be never ſo great, yet if his <hi>Zeal</hi> doth devour his <hi>Charity,</hi> ſowre and corrupt his Spirit, embit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and provoke him beyond what is ſeemly and conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, let his Cauſe be never ſo good, his Arguments ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo ſtrong, if they fail in this, all the reſt ſignifies not much; the lack of this one thing makes all the reſt defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, and for the moſt part unſucceſsful: For let me appeal to the moſt zealous <hi>Boarnarges</hi> of them all, can any man, who believes the Scripture, read the 13th Chapter of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> which treats purpoſely on the neceſſity and commendation of this moſt excellent Grace of Charity? I ſay, can he read that, and yet think it poſſible to be a good Chriſtian, or diſcharge a good <hi>Conſcience</hi> without it? For doth he not prefer it to the Tongues of Men and Angels; to the Gift of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, and working of Miracles? Nay, doth he not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Charity before the moſt comprehenſive Knowledge, miraculous Faith, liberal Almſ-deeds, and voluntary Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.1. &amp;c. <hi>Tho' I ſpeak with the Tongue of Men or Angels, tho' I have the gift of Prophecy, and underſtand all Myſteries, and all Knowledge, and tho' I have all Faith, and tho' I beſtow all my Goods to feed the Poor, and tho' I give my Body to be burnt, and have not Charity, it profiteth me nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Excellency and Advantage which Charity hath over all other Gifts of God's Holy Spirit, is proved at large from the wonderful good Offices and Effects there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. <hi>Charity ſuffers long, and is kind, envies not, vaunteth not it ſelf, is not pufft up, nor eaſily provoked
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60769:18"/>It rejoyceth</hi> in nothing but the <hi>Truth;</hi> it <hi>bears, believes, hopes, and endures all things;</hi> and therefore in the Concluſion he gives Charity the Preference of all others, <hi>Verſe.</hi> 13. <hi>Now abideth Faith, Hope, and Charity, theſe three, but the greateſt of theſe is Charity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Religion and conſequently our Church, though ſhe condemn Diviſions and Separations in all thoſe that leave off, and depart from her Communion; yet doth not wholly exclude them from her Charity, and therefore neither ſhould we from ours, meerly upon the Difference of Opinion, and eſpecially, if this Difference be for <hi>Conſcience</hi> ſake, and not out of <hi>Faction</hi> and <hi>Frowardneſs</hi> as I ſaid before, and would always be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood.</p>
            <p>And that I may not be thought to ſpeak without book, or affirm more then our Church will own, I ſhall refer you to that excellent piece call'd, <hi>The Moderation of the Church of England;</hi> out of which I have collected a few Paſſages, ſome whereof I have repeated more at large.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi> in her Injunctions, 1559. declares that [Her Majeſty being moſt deſirous of all other Earthly things, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her people ſhould live in Charity, both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God and Man, and therein abound in good works, Willeth and ſtraightly Commandeth all her Subjects to forbear all vain and contentious Diſputation in matters of Religion, and not to uſe in deſpite or rebuke of any Perſon, theſe Convitious (or <hi>Reviling</hi>) words of <hi>Papiſt, Heretick, Satiſmatick or Sacramentary,</hi> or any ſuch like expreſſions of Reproach] that is, we ought not to uſe theſe or the like Expreſſions in way of Reproach or vilify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of one another, as ſome in the heat of their wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Contention are very apt to do, to the exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating rather than convincing of Gainſayers.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:60769:19"/>
            <p>And King <hi>James,</hi> that Learned and Judicious Prince forbids [<hi>Pulpits</hi> to be made <hi>Paſquills.</hi>] And gave in charge to the Archbiſhop [That no Preacher of any De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination whatſoever, ſhall preſume to fall into bitter Invectives, and undecent Railings againſt the Perſons of either <hi>Papiſts</hi> or <hi>Puritans;</hi> but modeſtly and gravely, when they are occaſioned by their Text, free both the Doctrine and Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England</hi> from the Aſperſions of the Adverſaries.]</p>
            <p>To which we may add that memorable Paſſage out of Arch-biſhop <hi>Laud.</hi> [The Church of <hi>England</hi>] (ſaith he) is not ſuch a Shrew to her Children as to deny her Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, ordenounce an <hi>Anathema</hi> againſt them, if ſome peacebly diſſent in ſome particulars remoter from the Foundation.]</p>
            <p>And in the <hi>Homily</hi> againſt Contention, <hi>Serm.</hi> 1. We are exhorted therein, [ſo to read the Scripture, that by reading thereof we may be made the <hi>better Livers</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the more <hi>Contentious Diſputers.</hi> And if any thing be neceſſary to be taught, Reaſon'd, and Diſputed, let us do it with all Meekneſs, Softneſs, and Lenity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For it is better to give place Meekly, then to win the Victory with the breach of Charity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And again, We cannot be joyn'd to Chriſt our Head, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we be glued with Concord and Charity one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For he that is not of this Unity, is not of the Church of Chriſt, which is a Congregation or Unity toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and not a diviſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for the Readers further ſatisfaction therein, if he deſires it, I ſhall refer him, to the Book it ſelf, above mentioned, where the Learned Author gives an account of the Churches great <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Moderation</hi> through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the Parts and Branches of her Conſtitution which beſpeaks her of a truly <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and <hi>Primitive</hi> Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, wherein I wiſh all her Children would follow and Imitate her: And thereby ſet an Example to all thoſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60769:19"/>that are otherwiſe minded, or diſſent from our Church in <hi>this,</hi> as well as in other Inſtances of their Duty.</p>
            <p>For methinks thoſe that would ſet up for ſerious, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious Perſons, ought not to break the bond of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Charity, nor paſs the bounds of the Churches Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, by indulging their paſſions, or giving way to a peeviſh, froward, and Invidious Humour againſt all that differ from them in matters of Faith, and Doctrine, or purely out of Judgment, <hi>and Conſcience,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For I could never yet be perſwaded that Railing, and ill Language againſt <hi>Papiſts</hi> on the one hand, or <hi>Diſſenters</hi> on the other, is or ought to be a Diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing Character of a truly Loyal Son of the Church; ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when I conſider that moſt of thoſe that are addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted thereunto, are leaſt capable of convincing them otherways: Or if they are, yet this ſeems the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely way they can take for the doing of it, for we are told, <hi>That the wrath of Man worketh not the Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> James 1.20.</p>
            <p>Now if you would ſee the <hi>Indecency</hi> and Unſeemly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, of ill Language and reproachful Speeches, I need but remind you of the Rude and Slovenly Expreſſions, that are commonly uſed, and with a great deal of Venome ſpit in the Face of our Church.</p>
            <p>They can hardly find any other name for a <hi>Surpliſs,</hi> than that of a Superſtitious Rag and Relick of <hi>Popery;</hi> tho' there may be more <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Superſtition</hi> in their conceipt about it, then in the thing it ſelf; for ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not in the Object, but only in the mind or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of the Perſon that thinks ſo.</p>
            <p>Thus they have accuſtomed to revile our Liturgy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the notion of the <hi>Engliſh Maſs-book,</hi> the Biſhops and Governours of our Church are branded for <hi>Limbs of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt,</hi> and the Church her ſelf reputed for little better then <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> and <hi>Idolatrous:</hi> Neither have they learnt to ſtop here; but have adventured to fly in the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60769:20"/>Face of the <hi>Civil Government</hi> as well as the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, againſt both which they have Shot their Venemous <hi>Arrows, even bitier words. Pſalm.</hi> 64.3.</p>
            <p>But now I appeal to any ſober and ſerious Perſon, be he of what Perſwaſion he will, whether this be accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Principles of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> which is Profeſt in common by us all, or whether it is purely <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> which puts them upon ſuch unſeemly Practices; or is this Language fit to be beſtowed upon one of the moſt <hi>Eminent</hi> and <hi>Famous</hi> among all the Reformed Churches, and who, [without Vanity be it ſpoken,] hath been, one of the greateſt <hi>Bulworks</hi> againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> and <hi>Champion</hi> for the <hi>Reformation,</hi> and I hope, and pray daily it will continue to be ſo as long as God ſhall be pleaſed to continue Her or Himſelf a Church upon Earth.</p>
            <p>Now if Language of this Nature, tho' ariſing from the great and extraordinary Zeal of our Adverſaries, is ſo unhandſome and ill becoming in them towards us, why ſhould we think it any whit the more commendable and ſeemely in us toward them, or out of our mouths then out of theirs? That which is <hi>Evil</hi> and <hi>Offenſive</hi> in it ſelf, is and will be ſo, let who will be guilty of it.</p>
            <p>Wherefore methinks it would be more like Chriſtian, and make more for the credit of <hi>Religion</hi> and Honour of our Church, if we had more Charity and Kindneſs one for another, even in thoſe things, wherein we dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, ſo they be not Factious or Scandalous, nor have an ill influence on our Lives and Manners, rather than imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Example of ſome of our hot-headed <hi>Diſſenters</hi> in ſome of their <hi>worſt Qualities,</hi> to wit, in their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable Cenſures, and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian Revilings</hi> and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies. For the bitter and fiery Spirit of a <hi>Jewiſh Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot,</hi> is very unagreeable to the Meek, and Gentle Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of a true follower and Diſciple of Chriſt, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60769:20"/>to St. <hi>Luke</hi> 9.54, 55. <hi>And when his Diſciples,</hi> James <hi>and</hi> John <hi>ſaw this, they ſaid, Lord, wilt thou that we Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand Fire to come down from Heaven, and conſume them, even as</hi> Elias did. <hi>But he turned, and rebuked them, and ſaid, ye know not what manner of Spirit ye are of.</hi> And I ſhall be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to any man that ſhall be able to make out any other ſence and meaning thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>5thly</hi> A good <hi>Chriſtian</hi> ought to live according to his own <hi>Conſcience,</hi> rather then according to the <hi>Opinion</hi> of other Men. Beſure that man lives with the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and content to himſelf, who walks by the conſtant Rule of <hi>Gods Word,</hi> and not by that of the <hi>World,</hi> which conſiſts chiefly in <hi>Humour</hi> and <hi>Opinion,</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters almoſt every day, and upon the leaſt Occaſion. Whereas the Law of God is a ſure and ſtanding Rule, which being diligently heeded and attended unto, will not ſuffer us to go wrong or miſtake our way.</p>
            <p>'Tis impoſſible a man ſhould live ſo Regular in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, or carry himſelf ſo univerſally blameleſs and inof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive, as to gain the good Word and Opinion of all men, tho' he ſhould make it his chief ſtudy or ſole buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to do ſo; for men's Humours and Intereſts being ſo different and many times ſo contrary, that which likes one, doth not like another, and what this man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends, another may be apt to find fault withal.</p>
            <p>Nay, one and the ſame perſon is not always conſiſtent with himſelf, nor can keep long in the ſame mind: His thoughts and Judgments of things do often alter with his Affection and Intereſt, and notwithſtanding the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of things remains one and the ſame, yet his <hi>Opinion</hi> of them may not do ſo, and then they will be ſure to paſs their Cenſures on mens Perſons and Actions, according as they are in good or bad Humour, or as they judge, may make moſt for their preſent Intereſt.</p>
            <p>Now he undertakes a hard task indeed, who Studies to pleaſe thoſe, whoſe minds are ſo fickle and wavering, and whoſe Humours are made up of ſuch ſudden Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radictions.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:60769:21"/>
            <p>The People of the World are Maſters or our Credit and Reputation, which they may give or take from us at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as many times they do upon very ſlight or no ground at all: They depend upon the Opinion, which men are pleaſed to conceive of us, which they may alter when they liſt, whether we give cauſe for it, or no.</p>
            <p>But now no man or Number of men can be Maſters of our <hi>Conſciences;</hi> we may keep them Innocent and in Peace, let the World ſay or do what ſhe can: For tho' the deſerved <hi>Commendation</hi> of a Virtuous Action de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the Good Will of others; yet the <hi>Satisfaction</hi> it inwardly creates, is a <hi>Good</hi> they have nothing to do withal, and can never deprive us of, tho' they would. It concerns us therefore to take all the care we can of our <hi>Conſciences,</hi> and ſtudy rather to pprove our ſelves to <hi>them,</hi> than to the Multitude, the one being Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticable, when the other is not.</p>
            <p>Not that I would have any man careleſs of his Credit and good Name, for he that is not tender of his Fame, will hardly be ſo of his <hi>Conſcience;</hi> and the Reputation which is given to Virtuous Deeds, ought to be lookt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as no ſmall Incitement to the performance of them. But my meaning is, no man ought to be ſo Studious of Popular Applauſe, or affect the good Opinion of the World, by ſuch mean and unworthy Arts, as may tend to the Injuring of his <hi>Conſcience,</hi> or prejudice of his Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which he ows to God and the Church, to his Prince or Countrey. But let a man do, what he thinks in his <hi>Conſcience</hi> he ought to do, let him <hi>provide things ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt in the ſight of all men,</hi> run into no open Scandal, give no juſt or wilful cauſe of offence, and avoid as much as he can all Temptations or Provocations to evil, and then he ought not, he need not value the <hi>Talk of the World, nor Speech of People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Wiſe man, which in <hi>Solomon's</hi> ſenſe is a <hi>Prudent, Good</hi> man, ſhould firſt take care of doing his Duty, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:60769:21"/>then live above the ſpiteful Talk and Reports of the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, or regard their Cenſures no otherwiſe, then the Moon in the Fable did the barking of a Dog, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obſcur'd her Light, nor made her alter her Courſe. No, no, The inward content, which a man receives in the doing of a good Action is infinitely to be prefer'd before the Credit and Reputation, which it gains him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad; an Unwiſe man ſeeks his Reward and Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, where it is not to be found, namely from <hi>without,</hi> in the <hi>Goods</hi> and <hi>Poſſeſſions,</hi> in the Modes and Opinions of the World; but a good man finds it <hi>within</hi> himſelf, in the <hi>Right Order</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of his Mind and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and in the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> and <hi>Approbation</hi> of God and his own <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2d. Again, it concerns us not only to Live, but to Value our ſelves, and judge of our Eſtate towards God, according to the Teſtimony of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> rather than by the Fancy or Opinion which men are pleaſed to conceive of us.</p>
            <p>The generality of men, Eſteem and Value themſelves according to the <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Evil,</hi> that befalls them in the World, and happens to them in their outward Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns.</p>
            <p>If they are Sick or in Pain, in Poverty or Diſtreſs, under Misfortune or Diſgrace, they commonly bemoan their Condition, Lament their Miſerable Eſtate, and are apt to think themſelves the moſt Unfortunate Wretches of all others; When as all this hath befallen the very Beſt of men, who yet have been Happy amidſt the greateſt out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Misfortune, as long as they kept ſafe their Innocence, Anſwered the end of Affliction, and made an entire Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation of themſelves and their concerns unto the Will of God: And ſo long as a man doth this, he can never be Miſerable, neither ſhould he think himſelf ſo, let things go never ſo croſs, let the World Cenſure never ſo hard, or Reflect never ſo ſpiteful and ſevere.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:60769:22"/>
            <p>Alas, <hi>Happineſs</hi> and <hi>Miſery</hi> is not to be meaſured by the <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Evil,</hi> that befalls the Body, by Proſperity or Adverſity, by good Report or bad Report; otherwiſe who would be Innocent, or where ſhall we find a good man upon Earth, who hath eſcaped the Laſh of the tongue, or hath not been ill treated and miſrepreſented in one kind or other: I never yet did hear of ſuch a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and quite deſpair of ever doing ſo; and yet if meer Calumnies and Reproaches can make a man Guilty, then our Bleſſed Saviour muſt have been one of the Vileſt Creatures upon Earth; For no man could be more hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily Charg'd, and ſpitefully revil'd, and yet deſerve it leſs then he did, and all this from his own malicious Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-men the <hi>Jews</hi> and upon the account of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion too.</p>
            <p>But, God be praiſed, theſe things are not the <hi>meaſure</hi> of Guilt of Innocence: The beſt men would be moſt hardly dealt withal, were it in the power of the World to diſpenſe out their Rewards or Puniſhments. Guilt and Unhappineſs do not hang upon the Scandalous Tongues of Men, nor ſoar upon the Wings of Fame, neither do they flow from the Invidious Talk of Raſh and prejudiced People; but they have their Seat and Abode in the mind: As long as there is Peace in the <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and Innocence in the Soul, 'tis not in the Power of man or any thing under the Sun to make ſuch a Perſon bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or worſe, <hi>more</hi> or <hi>leſs</hi> Innocent or Guilty, Happy or Miſerable. For notwithſtanding all the ill things that may be ſaid or thought of ſuch a one, yet at the ſame time the Teſtimony of a good <hi>Conſcience</hi> is able to make amends for all: And notwithſtanding the <hi>Reproaches of the wicked</hi> may fall upon him; yet this is a <hi>Continual Feaſt</hi> ever at hand to welcome and entertain him, a rich Cordial to chear and revive him, being moreover the Pledge and Earneſt of a more <hi>Ample Reward.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:60769:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Which God of his Infinite mercy, Prepare us for, and bring us unto in his own due time, and that for the ſake of his beloved Son and our moſt Bleſſed Redeemer, Chriſt Jeſus the Righteous, to whom with the</hi> Father <hi>and</hi> Holy <hi>Spirit, be Aſcribed as is moſt due, all Honour and Glory, Praiſe and Adoration, now and for ever more,</hi> Amen, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
